<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/">

    <channel>
        <title>Martin Kleppmann's blog</title>
        <atom:link href="http://martin.kleppmann.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/</link>
        <description>Entrepreneurship, web technology and the user experience</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2011 15:59:27 PDT</lastBuildDate>
        <language>en</language>
        <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
        <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>

        
            <item>
                <title>What's so special about Y Combinator?</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/15/whats-so-special-about-y-combinator.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/15/whats-so-special-about-y-combinator.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/15/whats-so-special-about-y-combinator.html</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ Since we joined Y Combinator&#8217;s Summer 2010 funding cycle, I keep getting asked how much value we got from it, and whether I would do it again. tl;dr The short answer: we got a huge amount of value during the three-month main programme, and we are continuing to benefit all... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>Since we joined <a href='http://ycombinator.com/'>Y Combinator&#8217;s</a> Summer 2010 funding cycle, I keep getting asked how much value we got from it, and whether I would do it again.</p>

<p><strong>tl;dr</strong> The short answer: we got a huge amount of value during the three-month main programme, and we are continuing to benefit all the time from being part of YC. And yes, I would do it again without a moment&#8217;s doubt.</p>

<p>The long answer deserves a bit more explanation.</p>

<p>On the surface, it seems like the Y Combinator formula is <em>&#8220;money and mentoring for equity&#8221;</em>. That seems like a simple enough formula, and clones around the world are rushing to replicate it. Unfortunately I think they mostly miss the point, because there is so much more to YC which the others lack.</p>

<p>When <a href='http://rapportive.com'>we</a> applied to YC, we had already <a href='http://blog.rapportive.com/the-accidental-launch'>launched</a> and didn&#8217;t really need the $20k they were offering (investors had started contacting us from the day that Rapportive first hit the press). Looking at the other startups who joined YC at the same time of us, most of them got profitable or secured substantial angel/VC funding at good valuations soon afterwards. So although the money is nice, it&#8217;s probably not the main attraction.</p>

<p>As to mentoring, press and investor contacts&#8230; as an entrepreneur, you&#8217;re probably already quite good at getting attention and feedback from relevant people, using your personal network. How much more value could you get?</p>

<p><strong>Network and knowledge</strong></p>

<p>The things that are really special about Y Combinator, in my opinion, are less frequently talked about:</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p>There is a genuine, strong sense of camaraderie and mutual support amongst YC alumni. Many organisations claim to have strong alumni networks, but I have often found these claims to be empty words: often, the only participants in these networks are those who want to take, not those who want to give, because those who have something to give feel their time is wasted. It is hard to maintain a high standard in a network, and YC&#8217;s is the only example I have seen where the high standard is consistently upheld. Even the most busy founders of the most successful startups are genuinely supportive, and will spend surprisingly large amounts of time to answer questions, give practical advice, make introductions and recommendations, etc. They are real friends, not just utilitarian business contacts. This culture is truly remarkable.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>It sounds trite, but the YC partners are all really great people. They are exceptionally bright and talented, outspoken, honest, straight-to-the-point and totally bullshit-free &#8211; hardly anyone else I know even comes near in terms of these qualities. They have lots of time for their companies (surprisingly, given the number of companies they&#8217;ve funded), and I have only ever seen them do things that are good for founders. It seems altruistic, but Paul Graham maintains that it&#8217;s simply the best business strategy for YC.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>Between them, the YC partners have seen it all. They&#8217;ve seen big exits and small exits, profitable companies and train-wrecks, fast growth and slow growth, dream teams and founder disputes, and all manner of great ideas and screw-ups. Startups are unpredictable; you never know what surprises lie around the next corner. When we talk to YC, no matter whether we have good news or bad news, chances are that they&#8217;ve seen the situation before, and their pattern-matching will enable them to make good predictions.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>The YC team know everybody who&#8217;s worth knowing in the startup scene, and everyone respects them. This makes them ideally placed for introducing you to the kind of people you want to meet. Demo Day is one aspect of this, a maximum-efficiency batch process for introducing startups and investors to each other, but YC also make individual introductions all the time. They also know who is worth talking to, who is actively investing, and which people are just fishing for information.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>If there is a <a href='http://www.paulgraham.com/future.html'>change in the startup ecosystem</a>, YC are amongst the first to see it &#8212; because they have insight into a uniquely high proportion of startup deals, and they work actively to spot patterns and learn from them. As a YC startup, you get to hear about these changes first, something that you can use to your advantage.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>If you are new to Silicon Valley, like we were, YC is a fantastic way to get yourself established and find your feet. They are welcoming to outsiders, and you can bootstrap your valley network from those who already know their way around. You can celebrate with them when things go well, and to get encouragement from them in hard times. You couldn&#8217;t ask for a better group of people to hang out with.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>Because YC has a proven track record of funding great companies, being accepted to YC carries a strong signalling effect, making it more likely for others to <a href='http://thenextweb.com/industry/2011/02/07/y-combinator-partner-harjeet-taggar-start-fund-is-bad-news-for-bad-investors-interview/'>believe</a> that you are doing something interesting by default.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Being part of the best</strong></p>

<p>A lot of the points above are remarkable, but not intrinsically unique to Y Combinator; what&#8217;s particularly special about YC is that it is <strong>simply <a href='http://blog.businessofsoftware.org/2009/09/joel-spolskys-talk-at-business-of-software-2008-on-being-number-one.html'>number one</a></strong>. Being number one is very different from being number two or any number below.</p>

<p>One friend from our YC batch remarked at Demo Day: <em>&#8220;This room contains the future of the IT industry.&#8221;</em> He was right. Since many of the world&#8217;s best startups go through YC, they collectively form a force which has the power and drive to shape the entire industry for many years to come. That&#8217;s not because there is any centralised agenda; it&#8217;s more comparable to being a graduate from one of the top universities in the world.</p>

<p>Ever wonder why so many leading figures in business, science and politics are graduates of Harvard, Yale, Cambridge, Oxford, MIT or Stanford? I don&#8217;t think their teaching is really that much better than any other university, or than reading the textbooks by yourself. But you do get two valuable things from a top university:</p>

<ol>
<li>a signalling effect: other people can see that a reputable organisation thinks that at one point in your life (when you took your exams), you were reasonably motivated and not entirely stupid;</li>

<li>you build a network of talented people.</li>
</ol>

<p>I think we are seeing something similar with YC. The fact that YC has brought forth a number of successful startups is merely a correlation; by itself it doesn&#8217;t say anything about cause and effect. But when people see a correlation, it has a signalling effect nevertheless. (The reputation of a good university is also mostly due to the observed correlation between its graduates and their later success.)</p>

<p>Startups are risky and full of unknowns, and you as startup founder are in the business of convincing everyone that you are going to be the big, successful one. You need all the positive signals you can get.</p>

<p><strong>But is it worth the cost?</strong></p>

<p>Y Combinator takes 2&#8211;10% of your company&#8217;s equity. How do you figure out whether the value you get from YC is worth the cost? If you are wondering whether to apply for YC, this is probably the question you&#8217;re trying to answer.</p>

<p>Firstly, note this: <strong>dilution</strong> makes an <strong>incremental</strong> difference to your outcome: if you sell 5% of the company to an investor, you reduce your pay-out by 5% if you sell the company. However, whether you <strong>have or don&#8217;t have</strong> an investor can make a huge difference. Say you give 5% of the company to&#8230;</p>

<ul>
<li>someone who later makes that one critical introduction that leads to the deal which saves your company.</li>

<li>someone who helps you negotiate with your acquirer and doubles the value of your exit.</li>

<li>someone who encourages you to make a particular pivot, which turns out to unlock a billion-dollar market.</li>

<li>someone who prevents you from making a stupid mistake that would have set you back by 12 months.</li>
</ul>

<p>Whether any of these scenarios will actually happen is unknown in advance, but my point is: probability of success tends to move in discontinuous jumps. An extra per cent of equity may make absolutely no difference at all to your success, or it may turn out to make the difference between epic fail and massive win. A bit of equity may buy you an &#8220;unfair advantage&#8221;, or it may be a complete waste.</p>

<p>You need to figure out which investors might make the big difference, and which probably won&#8217;t. Your job as founder is to figure out how to play your cards such as to maximise the chances of massive win. Dilution changes incrementally, but probability of success is much more variable. Therefore, if you can figure out a way of substantially increasing your chances of success (putting yourself on the good side of some of those discontinuities), the equity cost is secondary. It&#8217;s not irrelevant, but as long as it&#8217;s in the right ballpark, it&#8217;s ok.</p>

<p>Of course you should be prudent to whom you give equity, but I would argue that if someone can give you &#8220;unfair advantages&#8221;, it&#8217;s well worth bringing them on board and not worrying too much about the cost.[<a href='#footnote-cap-table'>1</a>]</p>

<p>So, does Y Combinator give you that big advantage which has a disproportionately large positive impact on your chances of success?</p>

<p>I&#8217;d say yes. If you don&#8217;t need any of the benefits mentioned above, maybe not&#8230; but honestly, I&#8217;d be very surprised if your network and your group of advisors is already so perfect that you wouldn&#8217;t benefit from YC. Whether you&#8217;ve already launched or not makes very little difference.</p>

<p>YC is a package consisting of a variety of good things. In principle you may be able to assemble yourself a similar package from component parts &#8212; e.g. using <a href='http://angel.co/'>AngelList</a> for your investor intros, asking around to find suitable advisors, and spending lots of time networking and taking speculative meetings. But somehow that feels to me like buying individual CPUs and RAM and rack-mount cases to assemble your servers, when you could just spend 10 minutes to buy computing resources from Heroku, EC2 or Rackspace. It might make sense for some people, but for most of us, the time saving and assured quality you get from a good pre-built package is well worth a bit of extra cost. (That doesn&#8217;t mean you can&#8217;t use component parts <em>as well</em> &#8211; for example, we used AngelList to fill up our <a href='http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/02/rapportive-funding/'>seed round</a>.)</p>

<p>I hope you find this useful when deciding whether to apply to YC. :)</p>
<hr /><p id='footnote-cap-table'>[1]
In my opinion, the main reason to be careful with distribution of equity is not because dilution
reduces the size of your payout, but rather because you should avoid odd-looking things on your
cap table. Later investors will see weird things on the cap table during due diligence, may assume
that you are irresponsible in the way you run the business, and pull out of the deal. That's
something you can avoid by keeping your capital structure nice and clean. But honestly, no investor
in the world could possibly object to seeing YC on your cap table, because they know perfectly well
how much value YC brings. So that concern is irrelevant here.</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Accounting for Computer Scientists</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/07/accounting-for-computer-scientists.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/07/accounting-for-computer-scientists.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/07/accounting-for-computer-scientists.html</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ Every educated person really ought to have a basic understanding of accounting. Just like maths, science, programming, music, literature, history, etc., it&#8217;s one of those things which helps you make sense of the world. Although dealing with money is not much fun, it&#8217;s an unavoidable part of life, so you... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>Every educated person really ought to have a basic understanding of accounting. Just like maths, science, programming, music, literature, history, etc., it&#8217;s one of those things which helps you make sense of the world. Although dealing with money is not much fun, it&#8217;s an unavoidable part of life, so you might as well take a few minutes to understand it.</p>

<p>Sadly, in my opinion, most accountants do a terrible job of explaining their work in an accessible way; it&#8217;s a field full of jargon, acronyms and weird historical legacies. Even &#8220;Bookkeeping for Dummies&#8221; makes my head spin. Surely this stuff can&#8217;t be that difficult?</p>

<p>(We computing people are probably guilty of the same offence of bad explanations and jargon. The problem is, once you have become intimately familiar with a field, it&#8217;s very hard to imagine how you thought about things before you understood it.)</p>

<p>Eventually I figured it out: basic accounting is just graph theory. The traditional ways of representing financial information hide that structure astonishingly well, but once I had figured out that it was just a graph, it suddenly all made sense.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m a computer scientist, and I think of stuff in graphs all the time. If only someone had explained it like that in the first place! It would have saved me so much confusion. So I want to try to fix that. If you like graphs, then by the time you reach the end of this article, you should know everything you need in order to understand the financial statements for a small company/startup (and even calculate them yourself, in a spreadsheet or programming language of your choice).</p>

<p>It&#8217;s really not that hard. Let&#8217;s go!</p>

<p><strong>Accounts = Nodes, Transactions = Edges</strong></p>

<p>Say you go to the bagel shop and buy a Super Club bagel for $5 on the company credit card. You also visit some random Silicon Valley startup and buy one of their surplus Aeron chairs, second hand, for $500 (by writing a cheque from the company account). Those are two transactions. Each transaction is an edge in our graph, and the edge is labelled with the amount.</p>

<p>An edge always goes from one node to another. What are those nodes? Well, you can define them as you like (although there are some conventions). For now, let&#8217;s say:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting1.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting1.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>Let&#8217;s add some more details. You pay the $5 credit card bill from the company account. And where did the money in the company account come from in the first place? Ah, I see, you put in $5,000 of your savings to start the company. Ok, now the graph looks like this:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting2.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting2.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>Hopefully pretty self-explanatory so far. Money flows in the direction of the arrows.</p>

<p>Hungry once again, you go to the taqueria and buy a Super Burrito for $8 on the credit card. Now we could create another node for the taqueria, but this is starting to get messy &#8211; we don&#8217;t really care how much money we spent on bagels vs. how much on burritos. Let&#8217;s just lump them together as &#8220;food&#8221;. Also, &#8220;Random startup&#8221; is a bit unhelpful &#8211; I&#8217;ve already forgotten what those $500 were for. Let&#8217;s call it &#8220;furniture&#8221; instead.</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting3.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting3.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>See, that&#8217;s perfectly fine. We can have nodes which represent actual bank accounts or cards, others which represent people or companies, and others again which represent abstract categories like &#8220;food&#8221; or &#8220;furniture&#8221;. Just throw it all into the same graph.</p>

<p>Note also that you can have several edges between the same pair of nodes. You can keep track of the individual edges, or you can simply add them up. (Using the credit card, you spent a total of $13 on food.)</p>

<p><strong>Accounts have balances</strong></p>

<p>Every node in this graph is an <em>account</em> in accountant-speak (whether or not it is held by a bank), and every account has a <em>balance</em>. The balance is a single number for each account, and it is determined completely by the transactions in and out of the account:</p>

<ol>
<li>At the beginning of time, the value at each node is zero.</li>

<li>At each node, for each incoming edge, add the edge&#8217;s label to the node&#8217;s value; for each outgoing edge, subtract the edge&#8217;s label from the value.</li>
</ol>

<p>After you&#8217;ve processed all the edges, the value at each node is that account&#8217;s balance. Our graph now looks like this:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting4.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting4.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>Note that the account balances have two nice properties:</p>

<ol>
<li>Because every transaction appears twice &#8211; once positive and once negative &#8211; the sum of all account balances is always zero.</li>

<li>If you partition the set of nodes into any two disjoint sets, and add up all of the balances in each set, then the sum for the one set is always the negative sum of the other set (because, after all, they have to add up to zero).</li>
</ol>

<p>These properties are useful for sanity-checking your numbers; if they are violated, <em>&#8220;ur doin it wrong&#8221;</em>. (This is what accountants mean when they talk about &#8220;balancing the books&#8221;.)</p>

<p><strong>Doing business</strong></p>

<p>Strengthened by a bagel and a burrito, you go out and talk to some potential customers. And hey, they love your product! It has a price tag of $5,000, and you sell it to two big enterprise customers. One pays you right away (good stuff!); the other gives you $2,500 up front, but insists that before they pay the rest, you need to implement that additional feature you foolishly promised.</p>

<p>So you received $5,000 + $2,500 in cash from your customers, wired straight the company bank account. Let&#8217;s add that to the graph:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting5.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting5.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>But that&#8217;s not quite right. The price was $5,000 for each customer, and now it looks like you charged two different prices. How do we represent our arrangement with customer 2?</p>

<p>The solution is to deconstruct the deal into two separate transactions: the sale (in which the buyer agrees to buy, but no actual money changes hands) and the payment (when the cash actually hits your bank account). We can draw it like this:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting6.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting6.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>See what I&#8217;ve done here? I&#8217;ve just made up a new node, generically called it &#8220;sales&#8221;, and added the actual $5,000 sales as a transaction from this &#8220;sales&#8221; account to the customer accounts. Adding this extra node hasn&#8217;t changed your bank balance.</p>

<p>This makes sense when you think about the intuitive meaning of the balances. The balance of each customer&#8217;s account is the amount they owe you: customer 1 has fully paid up (their incoming and outgoing transactions add up to the same), so their balance is zero; customer 2 has contractually agreed to give you $5,000, but has so far only given you half of that, so their balance is $2,500.</p>

<p>And the balance on the sales account is the value of stuff you&#8217;ve sold. Or rather, the negative value. That looks a bit weird&#8230; but I&#8217;ll come back to that later. (BTW, if you wanted to separately track sales for different customers or different products, no problem &#8212; just add whatever nodes make sense for you. Just make sure that every transaction appears only once as an edge, otherwise you&#8217;re making stuff up!)</p>

<p><strong>Finishing off the example</strong></p>

<p>To round it off, let me add some more events to the story (= some more edges to the graph).</p>

<p>Not only have you made some sales, but now you also receive a $20,000 investment from Y Combinator &#8212; congratulations! You and your co-founder can now afford to pay yourselves a salary. You take $8,000 out of the company account.</p>

<p>Then you get set up with a company accountant, and they talk lots of jargon at you. For some strange reason they are obsessed with correctly accounting for your office chair; they want it to depreciate over four years, i.e. its value is gradually reduced to zero over the course of that time. Fair enough, you say (even though you couldn&#8217;t care less what your chair will be worth in four years&#8217; time &#8212; surely by that time you&#8217;ll be the next Google or Facebook, and you&#8217;ll have other things to worry about than chairs).</p>

<p>The resulting graph now looks like this:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting7.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting7.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>Note how I have represented the transactions:</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p>I have lumped together your founder investment with that of Y Combinator, under the heading of &#8220;capital&#8221;. Put simply, this is money you got into the company by selling your company&#8217;s shares, rather than by selling a product or service to a customer. As usual, you can split founders and YC into separate accounts if you feel like it.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>I&#8217;ve represented payroll (salaries) as just money straight out of the bank account. In reality it&#8217;s a bit more complicated due to taxes, healthcare, benefits, etc. but the principles stay the same. It&#8217;s just more nodes and edges in the graph.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>I made depreciation for one year (one quarter of $500 = $125) go <em>away</em> from the &#8220;furniture&#8221; account. Intuitively, this means that the balance of the &#8220;furniture&#8221; account is the value that your furniture still has now. Each year, you add another $125 edge from &#8220;furniture&#8221; to &#8220;depreciation&#8221;, until after four years, the balance of &#8220;furniture&#8221; drops to zero (assuming you haven&#8217;t bought any more chairs in the meantime, in your quest for world domination).</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>The profit and loss statement</strong></p>

<p>At this point, if you&#8217;re getting weary, I don&#8217;t blame you. But the good news: we&#8217;ve finished building our graph! Now I will show you how this graph representation maps to two standard financial statements most commonly used in managing a company: the profit and loss statement (&#8220;P&amp;L&#8221;), and the balance sheet. This is useful, because as a startup founder you&#8217;ll sooner or later have to discuss these documents with your investors/advisors, and so you might as well learn what the hell they mean.</p>

<p>In order to produce these statements, I need to get out the crayons. Here is the same graph as before, with the nodes coloured in:</p>
<p><a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting8.dot.png'>
  <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/accounting8.dot.png' alt='Graph representation of accounts' width='550' />
</a></p>
<p>Explaining the colours (putting the accounting terminology in brackets, since you&#8217;re likely to encounter these words):</p>

<ul>
<li>Green for <strong>stuff that you have</strong> (<em>&#8220;assets&#8221;</em>), e.g. money in the bank, or things which you bought and you could sell again, such as furniture. Also green for people/companies who <strong>owe you money</strong> (<em>&#8220;debtors&#8221;</em>, such as Customer 2), and people/companies to whom <strong>you owe money</strong> (<em>&#8220;liabilities&#8221;/&#8221;creditors&#8221;</em>, such as your upcoming credit card bill for that burrito).</li>

<li>Blue for <strong>sales of your product/service</strong> (<em>&#8220;revenue&#8221;</em>) and <strong>money you spent</strong> that you&#8217;re not going to get back (<em>&#8220;expenses&#8221;/&#8221;overheads&#8221;</em>). The office chair is green, because you could sell it again if you wanted to, but the bagel is blue, because once you&#8217;ve bought (and eaten) the bagel, that&#8217;s it &#8211; no going back.</li>

<li>Pink for <strong>money from investors</strong> (or yourself) that you got by selling shares (<em>&#8220;capital&#8221;</em>). (If you get a bank loan, that&#8217;s green, not pink, because you owe the bank to pay it back.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Every one of your nodes should fall into exactly one of these categories. If not, something has gone wrong, or you have discovered some bit of the accounting world that I don&#8217;t yet know about.</p>

<p>With these colours set, the profit and loss statement is simply <strong>a list of all the blue nodes</strong>, and the profit or loss of the company is the sum of all of the blue nodes&#8217; balances. The way we&#8217;ve calculated things, a negative value is a profit, and a positive value is a loss. That&#8217;s confusing, so you typically flip the sign when reporting the number (so that a profit is positive).</p>

<p>Written in the standard way, our P&amp;L looks like this:</p>
<table style='margin: 1.5em 0'>
  <tr>
    <th rowspan='2' style='font-variant: small-caps;'>Revenue</th>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Sales</td>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$10,000</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Total revenue</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$10,000</th>
  </tr>
  <tr style='height: 0.7em' />
  <tr style='margin-top: 1em'>
    <th rowspan='4' style='font-variant: small-caps;'>Expenses</th>
    <td>Payroll</td>
    <td style='text-align: right;'>$8,000</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Depreciation</td>
    <td style='text-align: right;'>$125</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Food</td>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$13</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Total expenses</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$8,138</th>
  </tr>
  <tr style='height: 0.7em' />
  <tr style='margin-top: 1em'>
    <th style='font-variant: small-caps;'>Total</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; font-weight: bold;'>Profit/Loss</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; font-weight: bold; text-align: right;'>$1,862</th>
    <td>(= total revenue - total expenses)</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<p>The meaning is fairly intuitive. You sold $10,000 worth of stuff, and spent only $8,138 in the process, so you made $1,862 profit.</p>

<p>The profit and loss statement is calculated over a period of time (usually a month, a quarter or a year), and it&#8217;s often interesting to compare two different periods. To calculate it for a period, filter your transactions to only include those which occurred within that period, and add up the account balances for just those transactions.</p>

<p>One thing to watch out for: profit doesn&#8217;t say anything about your bank account. The bank account is a green node, but we&#8217;re only looking at blue nodes here. In this example, you ended up with $23,995 in the bank, even though investors put in $25,000: you made a profit, yet still have less money in the bank than you did before, because Customer 2 hasn&#8217;t yet fully paid. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s possible for a company to be profitable but still run out of money!</p>

<p><strong>The Balance Sheet</strong></p>

<p>The balance sheet is a bit less intuitive than the P&amp;L, but it&#8217;s quite a powerful document. It summarises what the company currently has and doesn&#8217;t have, and why.</p>

<p>Remember what I said earlier about partitioning the nodes into two disjoint sets, and their summed balances adding to zero? That&#8217;s exactly what happens on the balance sheet. We take all of the nodes in the graph; on the one side we consider all of the green nodes, and on the other side all the blue and pink nodes. The sum of all of the blue and pink nodes&#8217; balances is minus the sum of all of the green nodes&#8217; balances.</p>

<p>Now, by convention, accountants flip the sign on all of the blue and pink nodes&#8217; balances, which means that the two sums end up being equal. And that&#8217;s why it&#8217;s called a balance sheet.</p>

<p>In our example, it looks like this:</p>
<table style='margin: 1.5em 0'>
  <tr>
    <th rowspan='4' style='font-variant: small-caps;'>Assets</th>
    <td>Bank account</td>
    <td style='text-align: right;'>$23,995</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Debtors</td>
    <td style='text-align: right;'>$2,500</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Furniture</td>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$375</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Total assets</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$26,870</th>
  </tr>
  <tr style='height: 0.7em' />
  <tr style='margin-top: 1em'>
    <th rowspan='2' style='font-variant: small-caps;'>Liabilities</th>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Credit card</td>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$8</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Total liabilities</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$8</th>
  </tr>
  <tr style='height: 0.7em' />
  <tr>
    <th colspan='2' style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; font-weight: bold;'>Total assets less total liabilities</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; font-weight: bold; text-align: right;'>$26,862</th>
  </tr>
  <tr style='height: 0.7em' />
  <tr style='margin-top: 1em'>
    <th rowspan='3' style='font-variant: small-caps;'>Equity</th>
    <td>Profit/Loss</td>
    <td style='text-align: right;'>$1,862</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888;'>Capital</td>
    <td style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; text-align: right;'>$25,000</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; font-weight: bold;'>Total equity</th>
    <th style='border-bottom: 1px solid #888; font-weight: bold; text-align: right;'>$26,862</th>
  </tr>
</table>
<p>The top block (assets and liabilities) corresponds to the green nodes in the graph, whilst the bottom block contains the pink node (capital) and the sum of all of the blue nodes. We already showed all of the detail for the blue nodes on the Profit and Loss statement above; on the balance sheet we can sum them all up to a single number.</p>

<p>Some more sign-flipping has occurred here: I&#8217;ve written liabilities, equity and P&amp;L with their signs flipped (which usually, but not always, has the effect of making the numbers positive). That doesn&#8217;t change anything fundamental about the graph structure, it just puts things into the conventional schema.</p>

<p>So how can you interpret the balance sheet? There are various things you can read from it. You can see how much money is in the bank, and how much of that money has already been promised to other people (liabilities). You can see how much of the money in the bank came from investors, vs. how much came from sales. And it shows how much money is due to come in soon, from sales that have closed but haven&#8217;t yet been fully paid.</p>

<p>The total of the balance sheet is a lower bound on the value of your company. It&#8217;s a very pessimistic figure &#8212; it assumes that your team, your technology, your brand etc. are all worth precisely nothing; if your company raises money from investors, your valuation will be much higher than the balance sheet figure, since that valuation includes the value of team, technology, brand etc in the form of a wild guess. In established companies you can find &#8220;intangible assets&#8221; on the balance sheet, but since they are very hard to value, I suspect it&#8217;s not worth bothering with unless you know what you are doing.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s the end of our whirlwind tour through the world of accounting. If you&#8217;re a real accountant reading this, please forgive my simplifications; if you spot any mistakes, please let me know. For everyone else, I hope this has been useful. To find out when I write something new, please <a href='http://twitter.com/martinkl'>follow me on Twitter</a> or put your email address in this box:</p>
<form name='mc-embedded-subscribe-form' class='validate' method='post' action='http://rapportive.us2.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=9a1adaf549282981a96e171d1&amp;id=4543b695f6' id='mc-embedded-subscribe-form' target='_blank'>
    <fieldset>
        <div class='mc-field-group'>
            <label for='mce-EMAIL'>Email:</label>
            <input name='EMAIL' class='required email' id='mce-EMAIL' type='text' value='' />
            <input name='subscribe' class='btn' id='mc-embedded-subscribe' type='submit' value='Subscribe' />
        </div>
        <div id='mce-responses'>
            <div class='response' id='mce-error-response' style='display:none' />
            <div class='response' id='mce-success-response' style='display:none' />
        </div>
    </fieldset>
</form><p class='disclaimer'>
    I won't give your address to anyone else, won't send you any spam, and you can unsubscribe at any time.
</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Having a launched product is hard</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/12/21/having-a-launched-product-is-hard.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/12/21/having-a-launched-product-is-hard.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/12/21/having-a-launched-product-is-hard.html</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ Over the last 6 months, we have been learning what it means to support a launched product. Some background: Rapportive launched in March 2010, and we joined Y Combinator for the Summer 2010 batch from June to August. Even though it was fantastic to have users and solid growth, it... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>Over the last 6 months, <a href='http://rapportive.com'>we</a> have been learning what it means to support a launched product.</p>

<p>Some background: Rapportive <a href='http://blog.rapportive.com/the-accidental-launch'>launched</a> in March 2010, and we joined <a href='http://ycombinator.com/'>Y Combinator</a> for the Summer 2010 batch from June to August. Even though it was fantastic to have users and solid growth, it was actually a very frustrating time for us as a team.</p>

<p>We found the downside of having launched, namely that we ended up spending the entire 3 months of Y Combinator (and probably another month either side) doing the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Answering many, many support emails and tweets</li>

<li>Raising <a href='http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/02/rapportive-funding/'>our seed round</a></li>

<li>Stopping our infrastructure from collapsing under our user growth</li>

<li>Responding to press and bloggers</li>

<li>Reading resumés and interviewing job candidates</li>

<li>Fixing gnarly bugs in production</li>

<li>Applying for visas, so that we could work in the US</li>

<li>Attending YC dinners and office hours</li>
</ul>

<p>By contrast, the ideal world of Y Combinator involves spending 3 months:</p>

<ul>
<li>Moving your product forward</li>

<li>Attending YC dinners and office hours</li>
</ul>

<p>Although all the things we were doing were valuable &#8212; even spending so much time on support is valuable, because we learnt a lot about our users, and we turned lots of people from angry strangers into enthusiastic supporters &#8212; it was incredibly frustrating. Our product development was almost stalled for months on end. And all the while, our YC batchmates were demoing new features every week, and getting a massive high from the productive flow of developing their products at a rapid pace.</p>

<p>So I am perhaps a bit envious of those who could move ahead rapidly and build their product without having to worry about supporting users or keeping their database alive. On the other hand, I am of course hugely grateful for our users who use and <a href='http://rapportive.com/buzz'>love our product</a> every day. I wouldn&#8217;t have it any other way.</p>
<p style='text-align: center'>
  <a href='http://adam.heroku.com/past/2008/4/23/the_startup_curve/'>
    <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/12/yc_whiteboard.jpg' height='379' alt='Photo of whiteboard at YC, showing curve of The Process' width='500' />
  </a>
</p>
<p>Fortunately, we are not the first to experience this. At the YC office there is a whiteboard, now carrying somewhat iconic status, which reminds every single YC founder of <em>&#8220;The Process&#8221;</em>: once a startup has launched, the novelty will wear off, and the team will find itself in the <em>&#8220;Trough of Sorrow&#8221;</em>. We know what the Trough of Sorrow looks like. I have just described it. It&#8217;s not very much fun.</p>

<p>But here is good news: Rapportive now seems to have journeyed on to the next phase, we have made <a href='http://blog.rapportive.com/grow-your-network-with-rapportive'><em>&#8220;Releases of Improvement&#8221;</em></a>, and things are looking hopeful. Are we in those <em>&#8220;Wiggles of False Hope&#8221;</em>? Who knows. But hey, the money is in the bank, the visas are in our passports, the infrastructure has got a lot more robust, and most importantly, our product development is moving again. We have some really cool stuff coming soon. The hope is real. And we seem to have managed to avoid the <em>&#8220;Crash of Ineptitude&#8221;</em>.</p>

<p>So what have we learnt?</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p>Visibly iterating and improving the product is arguably the most important thing a startup should be doing, but sadly, other stuff has an uncanny ability to distract you away from product work. <a href='http://www.paulgraham.com/top.html'>Paul Graham has written</a> about money matters and disputes being particularly bad in this regard. That is true, and I would add server firefighting, recruitment and immigration to the list.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>In order to get back into a flow of product development, we are now deliberately shunning distractions like recruitment and fundraising. We obviously can&#8217;t ignore these things forever, but for now it&#8217;s best for the business if we stay focussed on the thing we do best: making a <a href='http://www.paulgraham.com/good.html'>product that people want</a>. (We&#8217;re keeping one distraction, namely support, because it is so important. But we are rotating support duties so that most of the team can ignore it at any given moment.)</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>Be grateful if you carry a US passport.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>Sometimes you just have to wade through a patch of mud, and there&#8217;s no way round it. But as long as you keep your eyes forward and keep moving, you&#8217;ll get through it, and things will brighten up.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p style='text-align: center'>
  <a href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/performable/4792109640/sizes/l/in/set-72157623602121734/'>
    <img src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/12/strategic_plan.jpg' height='335' alt='Poster: We have a strategic plan. It&apos;s called doing things.' width='500' />
  </a>
</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Intuition has no transfer encoding</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/10/30/intuition-has-no-transfer-encoding.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/10/30/intuition-has-no-transfer-encoding.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=400</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ Intuition is really annoying sometimes. Actually, I love intuition, because almost all my thinking is based on it. I don’t think I am very good at analysing and thinking things through logically. Often I just have a feeling about how something should be, and then sometimes I post-rationalise it. Not... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p><strong>Intuition is really annoying sometimes.</strong></p>

<p>Actually, I love intuition, because almost all my thinking is based on it. I don’t think I am very good at analysing and thinking things through logically. Often I just have a feeling about how something should be, and then sometimes I post-rationalise it.</p>

<p>Not everybody’s mind works this way; if yours works like this too, you will think this is completely obvious. If not, you probably know people of this type, who can just assert “I think we should do it this way” and turn out to be right in maybe 75% of cases. Intuition is never perfect, but I love it, because it often gives a “good enough” answer very quickly, or at least provides some pointers towards places where it would be worth spending a bit more time analysing.</p>

<p>The thing that I find so annoying about intuition is that it is <strong>very hard to communicate</strong>. Let me explain.</p>

<p>Intuition is built from a large number of experiences: you grow up, you go through life, you meet people, you go to places, you read stuff, you make up stuff. There is no chance you can remember all the things you ever experience in factual detail, because that would be an overwhelmingly huge amount of information. But those things are nevertheless not forgotten: each experience leaves a trace, a tiny shadow of memory, so your thinking afterwards is ever so slightly different from the way it was before.</p>

<p>Over the course of years, those tiny traces are aggregated, and what you get out at the end is an intuitive understanding of how the world works (or rather, how those parts of the world which you have experienced work). Think of it like very light crayon touches, in the hands of an artist, gradually forming to be a beautiful picture — except that the picture is never complete, and always evolving.</p>
<object height='311' width='508'>
    <param name='movie' value='http://www.youtube.com/v/5OLP4nbAVA4?fs=1&hl=en_US' />
    <param name='allowFullScreen' value='true' />
    <param name='allowscriptaccess' value='always' />
    <embed src='http://www.youtube.com/v/5OLP4nbAVA4?fs=1&hl=en_US' allowfullscreen='true' type='application/x-shockwave-flash' allowscriptaccess='always' height='311' width='508' />
</object>
<p>With that intuition, when you encounter a new situation, it doesn’t matter that you haven’t encountered the exact same situation before: your brain does an approximate matching of the new situation with your mental model of the world, and immediately predicts the right answer. It doesn’t even need to search through memories, because the picture of the world in your head is already the fully aggregated sum of your experiences.</p>

<p>(As a second step, you will typically compare your gut reaction to specific memories, to check whether the results agree. But that’s another topic.)</p>

<p><strong>A tale of bitmaps and vector graphics</strong></p>

<p>The way I imagine the brain stores intuition is a bit like a huge bitmap image, with lots and lots of pixels [<a href='#intuition-footnote'>1</a>]. When a new piece of information comes in, the brain’s massively parallel processing structure takes the new information, combines it with the existing image, correlates, interpolates, extrapolates, and produces an answer in an instant.</p>

<p>But what if you want to teach your intuition to someone else? You can’t tell that person all the things you ever experienced in your life, because that would be far too much, and you’ve forgotten and assimilated most of those memories anyway. But that mental bitmap is also a terrible transfer format: our mouths and hands are extremely slow communication channels, making it impossible to get the bitmap out of your brain. Imagine reading out the individual pixel values of a bitmap image over the phone. It would take hours before the other person had even the vaguest, blurriest idea of the outlines of the image. And it would take years to fill in the detail.</p>

<p>So&#8230; if you want to transfer that bitmap out of your brain and into someone else’s, even approximately, you have to turn that bitmap into a vector graphic.</p>

<p>In vector graphics, if you choose your points and curves carefully, you can communicate the general structure of a picture very succinctly. You can enable the other person to very quickly get a rough idea of your thinking. Of course it won’t have all the colourful detail until you add lots more information, but that’s ok. And once you have analysed your picture into a vector form, you have actually gained a better understanding of what it is really about, you can zoom in to see a higher resolution, and you may be able to spot patterns that you weren’t previously aware of.</p>

<p>Of course, the problem: turning bitmaps into vector graphics is hard. Computer Vision researchers are always thinking about better algorithms for doing it.</p>

<p>And to return from our image analogy to the topic of intuition: expressing intuitive knowledge in a structured form is really hard.</p>

<p><strong>Vectorising intuition</strong></p>

<p>As a child, when you learn your first language by imitating sounds and by being continually corrected by your parents, you are building an intuition for the way that language works. You start off with <em>ga ga ga</em>, and it takes years before you can speak a coherent sentence; later, as time goes on and you grow up, you get quite good at it. Because your brain stores a pre-rendered representation of the language, you can speak and understand it easily and quickly.</p>

<p>When an adult learns a foreign language, by contrast, the usual way of learning it is by studying grammar, vocabulary and carefully chosen texts. The rules of grammar and the structure of the syllabus are a kind of vector representation of the language, optimised for giving the learner a rough overview of the language structure and helping them construct useful sentences as quickly as possible.</p>

<p>It is perfectly possible for an adult to go to a foreign country with no prior knowledge of the language, and to learn to speak it without formal grammar or syllabus, in the same way as a child does. However, most adults prefer to learn a language in a systematic manner, presumably because learning in “vectorised” form allows you to be much faster in getting to the stage where you can have an interesting conversation.</p>

<p>No matter which way you learn the basics, it always takes years to reach native proficiency in a language; that is unavoidable, because in the end you can’t get around learning a huge amount of subtle details and building your own intuition. (Even if represented in vector form, complicated curves and shadings require a large number of points.) The difference is in the time it takes to grok the core concepts.</p>

<p><strong>But here comes the important bit.</strong> When it comes to learning languages, most languages have benefitted from decades (if not centuries) of research and systematisation efforts by many intelligent people. For most languages, grammar and learning techniques are very well understood. But what if you want to communicate some intuition that <strong>only you</strong> have? Well, you have to do the vectorising yourself.</p>

<p>When you have built an intuition in a specific area that is not well-known — say, with regard to some arcane or new technology, or with regard to your company’s business strategy — then there is no existing grammar you can refer to. You are like a linguist, <a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Everett'>going into the Amazonian Jungle</a> to document mysterious languages not yet known to the outside world. You have to observe the systematic parts and the exceptions, and formulate the grammar yourself.</p>

<p>Turning your intuitive bitmap into a vector form that you can communicate&#8230; is hard. Very hard. But you need to figure it out.</p>

<p><strong>Why is this important?</strong></p>

<p>Well, there’s only so far that a single person’s intuition can reach. If you want to build great things and change the world, you need much more than a single person’s brain can hold. You need both depth and breadth: fine-grained intuition in specific technical fields requiring expertise, and also a greater variety of perspectives than a single person can have experienced.</p>

<p>You need to combine the intuitions of several people, i.e. you have to form a team. And in order to combine your intuitions, you need to communicate and explain them. Why? Because otherwise you have no way of resolving differences, and no way of learning from each other and improving.</p>

<p>By default, intuition comes without a reason attached: you ‘simply know’ that the answer is X, but you don’t know why. The problem arises when your colleague ‘simply knows’ that the answer is Y, where X≠Y, and doesn’t know a reason either. (Maybe X and Y are not completely contradictory, but rather partially overlapping ideas or differences in emphasis. Different nevertheless.) At that point either one has to overrule the other (which would defeat the goal of forming a team in the first place), or you have to rationalise the intuition, untangle the pre-aggregated reasoning, and communicate it in terms which the other person can understand.</p>

<p>What if you could understand the structure of both X and Y, and the reasoning behind it, and thus manage to synthesise the two? That is a lot of effort, but I am increasingly thinking that figuring out how to communicate your intuition is one of the most valuable things you can do in a team. For if you can combine your mental image of the world with other people’s, you can build something much greater than each of you. Your thoughts can be superhuman, in some sense. And that, if you can figure it out, is a huge advantage you can have.</p>

<p>A startup is a really interesting environment to try this kind of thing, because you can be as choosy as you want about the people you work with. You can pick like-minded people, and together work towards that shared intuition. You can build a good, well-founded, shared intuition of who your customers are and what they want. And if you can attain that shared intuition, you&#8217;re well underway to success.</p>

<p><strong>Footnote:</strong></p>
<a name='intuition-footnote'>
</a>
<p>[1] I&#8217;m not sure what each individual pixel represents. In mathematical terms, a picture is a function mapping from 2D space to colour, and a bitmap approximates this function by sampling at regularly spaced values of the input. Along that line of thinking, the mind is probably a function mapping from sensory inputs and memories to explanations and actions (or something along those lines — I&#8217;m not a neuroscientist). This function can be represented as lots of individual data points (&#8220;London &amp; lunchtime &amp; hunger &amp; last had Falafel 10 days ago → go to the King of Falafel&#8221;), which is bitmap-like, or in some systematic manner (&#8220;I like to eat falafel for lunch. For example, in London, the King of Falafel is good.&#8221;), which is vector-like, omitting redundant information (lunchtime and hunger are strongly correlated, so mentioning both is fairly redundant) and emphasising structure or dependencies (the King of Falafel only exists in London). However, as you can see, his only vaguely makes sense. The bitmap/vector analogy is itself an example of a piece of intuition that I&#8217;m trying to communicate to you right now.</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Good things are hard to articulate</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/08/31/good-things-are-hard-to-articulate.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/08/31/good-things-are-hard-to-articulate.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=394</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ If you have a stone in your shoe, it&#8217;s easy to articulate what is wrong (&#8220;something is hurting my foot!&#8221;). But if you don&#8217;t have a stone in your shoe, you don&#8217;t go around rejoicing with every step. If you have just removed a stone, you may be pleased for... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>If you have a stone in your shoe, it&#8217;s easy to articulate what is wrong (&#8220;something is hurting my foot!&#8221;). But if you don&#8217;t have a stone in your shoe, you don&#8217;t go around rejoicing with every step. If you have just removed a stone, you may be pleased for a few seconds to have removed the irritation, but things very quickly return to normal.</p>

<p>The bad things keep sticking around and irritating us, whereas the good things are quickly taken for granted. The bad things are often easy to describe, whereas the good things are sometimes just the absence of a bad thing &#8212; the absence of some irritation.</p>

<p>This is a fundamental asymmetry, and it has lots of implications, big and small. For example, a big implication is the development of human society and technology. Because we are more prone to noticing bad things, and bad things keep bugging us, we try to fix bad things and make them go away. So humans invented tools (to stop hurting their fingers), agriculture (to stop hunger and laborious hunting/gathering), medicine (to stop their family members from dying), writing (to stop forgetfulness) and the internet (to stop the slowness of paper communication). Over history, humans have continuously taken stuff that is bad, and tried to make it better. Now that we have all these good things (tools, agriculture, medicine, writing, internet), we mostly take them for granted and don&#8217;t think about them any more.</p>

<p>(Some things that humans invented turned out to have bad side-effects besides their intended good effect. Take weapons as an example: intended to stop the hungry neighbours from stealing our food, but the idea got taken a bit too far. But that&#8217;s a different story.)</p>

<p>There are also other, less grandiose consequences of bad things being more noticeable. For example, when I was writing music and song lyrics, I found it comparatively easy to write about themes like conflict, struggle and sadness; writing about good things, however, was much harder. It would often just sound trite, banal and uninteresting.</p>

<p>How do you articulate those things that are good? Part of the point of this very essay is to see if I can write about things being good without just being incredibly boring. And what do I do? Complain about the fact that it&#8217;s hard to express things that are good. I complain. I am irritated that bad things are easier to write about than good things. And so I write about that irritation, thereby locking myself in a self-referential loop.</p>

<p>How annoying. Let&#8217;s talk about the good things again.</p>

<p>An observation. If bad things are much more noticeable than good things, that means that it&#8217;s very easy to lose sight of all the good things. In fact, it probably means that we are surrounded by lots of wonderful things that we&#8217;ve simply forgotten about. It might even be that the vast majority of things around us are good, and we are just failing to notice them!</p>

<p>We need to consciously remind ourselves of the good things from time to time, to avoid getting too bogged down in the bad things. That cannot mean getting complacent; it just means enjoying and appreciating life.</p>

<p>For example, I am writing this essay on a mobile phone (good) connected to the internet (good) while sitting in the sunshine (good) in a park (good) in San Francisco (good). I am wearing comfortable clothes (good) and don&#8217;t have any stones in my shoes (good). I live in a peaceful age (good) in a peaceful society (good). I am educated (good), healthy (good), don&#8217;t need to worry about being able to afford the rent (good) and I have a wonderful family (good). I look forward to sending this essay to Rita (good) to see what she thinks. (Hopefully it&#8217;s not too bad.)</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Valuation caps on convertible notes, explained with graphs</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/05/05/valuation-caps-on-convertible-notes-explained-with-graphs.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/05/05/valuation-caps-on-convertible-notes-explained-with-graphs.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=378</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ When you&#8217;re an entrepreneur out to raise funding, you&#8217;re faced with a whole lot of legal and financial jargon, and getting your head around it takes a lot of valuable time &#8211; that&#8217;s time in which you&#8217;re not doing the things which really matter (namely making your product better, making... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>When you&#8217;re an entrepreneur out to raise funding, you&#8217;re faced with a whole lot of legal and financial jargon, and getting your head around it takes a lot of valuable time &#8211; that&#8217;s time in which you&#8217;re not doing the things which really matter (namely making your product better, making your existing customers happy and acquiring new customers).</p>

<p>But actually, if explained properly, most of the legal and financial stuff isn&#8217;t that complicated. The legal documents do a terrible job of explaining, because they define everything in legalese prose. Graphs make it much clearer, as Leo Dirac has shown in his wonderful <a href='http://www.slideshare.net/leodirac/5minute-primer-on-vc-term-sheets'>graphical explanation of liquidation preferences</a>. You should go and look at that presentation.</p>

<p>I&#8217;d like to explain a different financial concept, namely the <strong>valuation cap on convertible notes</strong>. It took me several hours to get my head around it, so I&#8217;d like to save you those hours.</p>

<p><strong>The pros and cons of convertible notes</strong></p>

<p>I assume you know what a convertible note (aka convertible loan) is: instead of buying shares in your startup, the investor just gives you the money on a loan with some nominal interest rate. And you promise that when you raise your next round of funding, the loan converts into shares as if they had put that money in during that second round. Since the investor took additional risk by backing you early, they get a discounted share price (they get more shares than someone who puts in the same amount of money in the second round), and that discount is fixed and agreed upon beforehand. It&#8217;s typically between about 15% and 30%.</p>

<p>The good thing about convertible notes is that they require less paperwork (and are thus faster to get done), and &#8211; in theory &#8211; don&#8217;t require you to set a valuation, because the share price will be determined in the next round. However, many investors don&#8217;t like them. If the company is really successful (as everybody hopes it will be) and the valuation in the next round is high, then the investors don&#8217;t get any of that increase in value &#8211; they just get their fixed discount, and that&#8217;s it.</p>

<p>With some <a href='http://www.crunchbase.com/person/ron-conway'>big-name investors</a>, the company&#8217;s value goes up simply by being associated with the big name. Naturally, the investor will also want to benefit from that increase in value, because otherwise there&#8217;s not much incentive for them to help.</p>

<p>Enter the valuation cap, which appears to now be a standard term of convertible notes, in Silicon Valley at least. The cap is the convertible note investor basically saying: <em>&#8220;If things go ok, I&#8217;m happy with my fixed 20% discount. But if you do really well, I want us to treat it as if I had bought shares in the first place.&#8221;</em> (That way they benefit more from the success.)</p>

<p>So you went for a convertible note hoping that you wouldn&#8217;t have to set a valuation for your startup. Well, with the valuation cap you don&#8217;t strictly have a valuation, but you <em>do</em> have a <em>range of valuations</em>: the company is certainly not worth less than X, and not worth more than Y.</p>

<p>In effect, someone has now got to decide on a valuation, which is a notoriously unscientific thing. How do you come up with reasonable numbers? You need to somehow build an intuition for what this stuff means.</p>

<p><strong>How to determine your valuation cap</strong></p>

<p>The best way to think about it is to start with some guesswork numbers, consider a range of different scenarios, and work out the consequences. Then you can decide which consequences are unacceptable, and work backwards.</p>

<p>Let&#8217;s work through an example. Say you&#8217;re a small startup team raising your first seed round, and you expect to raise a Series A from VCs sometime in future. Your input variables are:</p>

<ul>
<li>the amount you&#8217;re raising on the convertible note (say $500k),</li>

<li>the conversion discount of the note (say 20%),</li>

<li>the pre-money valuation cap of the note (say $4m),</li>

<li>the percentage of your company which the VCs will take in your Series A (say 30%),</li>

<li>the amount of money you expect to raise in your Series A (say somewhere between $1m and $5m).</li>
</ul>

<p>There are a few other parameters (like the interest rate on the loan, and the time between the seed round and the series A), but they ought to have only a minor impact.</p>

<p>The biggest unknown here is the amount you&#8217;ll want to raise in your Series A, so let&#8217;s look at a range of scenarios for that value, and take the other variables to be fixed.</p>

<p>There are two consequences of the numbers which are useful to think about:</p>

<p><strong>1. What share of the company do the convertible note investors own after the Series A?</strong></p>

<p>We assumed above that after the Series A, the Series A investors own 30% of the company. But how much do the seed investors own after converting their note into shares?</p>
<img class='aligncenter size-full wp-image-379' src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/05/Valuation-Cap-demo-1.png' height='402' alt='How much equity does the note convert into?' width='550' />
<p>Without the valuation cap, the seed investors end up with an ever diminishing share of the company as the valuation increases. The effect of the cap is that the convertible note investors are guaranteed a certain share of the company, even if you get a <a href='http://techcrunch.com/2010/03/25/four-vc-firms-battle-for-foursquare-valuation-goes-stratospheric/'>Foursquare valuation</a>.</p>

<p>That minimum share is: (1 &#8211; [series A investor ownership] ) * [amount raised on conv note] / [valuation cap]. (The first factor takes into account the Series A dilution.) In this example, the note will convert into a minimum of (1&#8211;0.3) * $0.5m / $4m = 8.75% of the company&#8217;s shares.</p>

<p><strong>2. What effective discount are the convertible note investors getting relative to the Series A investors?</strong></p>

<p>If you didn&#8217;t have a cap, you would simply give a fixed (say 20%) discount when the note converts into shares. But when you have a cap, and your Series A valuation hits the cap, you&#8217;re fixing the price for the early investors, while the incoming Series A investors might be paying a lot more per share. So you are effectively giving a greater than 20% discount in that case.</p>
<img class='aligncenter size-full wp-image-380' src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/05/Valuation-Cap-demo-2.png' height='403' alt='Effective discount on conversion' width='550' />
<p>I find this graph interesting, because it&#8217;s basically a measure of &#8220;how annoyed the VCs are going to be about the convertible note&#8221;. &#8211; Imagine you&#8217;re at the theatre, and you know that for the same ticket you paid 2 or even 3 times as much as the guy sitting next to you. You would not be happy, because it just doesn&#8217;t feel fair. If your valuation goes substantially above the cap, there can be a big difference in share price.</p>

<p>Of course, if your startup is awesome and investors are desperate to be part of your round, this probably won&#8217;t be an issue. And of course, maybe such a large discount is entirely fair if your Angel investors add a lot of value beyond the money they put in. But it&#8217;s a factor to keep in mind. At least with a graph like this you can start thinking about your numbers usefully.</p>

<p><strong>Postscript</strong></p>

<p>None of this gives you an immediate answer to the question &#8220;what should we write on our convertible note term sheet?&#8221;, but at least you should now be able to think about valuation caps from a few different angles.</p>

<p>Disclaimer: neither am I a lawyer nor do I have much experience with this stuff, so my explanation may be horribly flawed or simply wrong. (If you find a mistake, please let me know.)</p>

<p>You can <a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/05/Valuation-Cap-demo-for-blog.xlsx.zip'>download the Excel spreadsheet</a> which I used to generate these graphs. An interesting alternative way of looking at this would be to assume a fixed Series A amount, and instead work out what happens when you vary the valuation cap. I&#8217;ll leave that as an exercise for you, dear reader.</p>

<p>Incidentally, our awesome startup, <a href='http://rapportive.com'>Rapportive</a>, is raising a seed round at the moment. It&#8217;s filling up quickly, so please <a href='mailto:martin@rapportive.com'>get in touch soon</a> if you may be interested. The terms may have certain similarities with my example here, or they may not &#8211; I couldn&#8217;t say. ;-)</p>

<p><strong>Update (11 June 2010):</strong> Packed the Excel spreadsheet in a ZIP file to fix download problems.</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Our social future</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/04/09/our-social-future.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/04/09/our-social-future.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=376</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ You know you&#8217;re doing something good if someone you&#8217;ve never met before spontaneously comes up to you and asks: &#8220;Are you with Rapportive? Just wanted to say that I love it.&#8221; He could recognise me because we had exchanged emails, and he had therefore seen my photo in Rapportive next... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>You know you&#8217;re doing something good if someone you&#8217;ve never met before spontaneously comes up to you and asks: &#8220;Are you with Rapportive? Just wanted to say that I love it.&#8221;</p>

<p>He could recognise me because we had exchanged emails, and he had therefore seen my photo in Rapportive next to my email.</p>

<p>This is our social future. We&#8217;re busy creating it.</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Hey, what happened just then?</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/03/31/hey-what-happened-just-then.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/03/31/hey-what-happened-just-then.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=372</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ There are moments in life where everything suddenly changes. Do you know what I mean? Those moments are rare, but on some occasions, your entire outlook on life can fundamentally change overnight. This particular story begins about a year ago. I had just finished a few web development contracts, and... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>There are moments in life where everything suddenly changes. Do you know what I mean? Those moments are rare, but on some occasions, your entire outlook on life can fundamentally change overnight.</p>

<p>This particular story begins about a year ago. I had just finished a few web development contracts, and had started to build my automated web testing tool, <a href='http://go-test.it'>Go Test It</a>. At the time I thought Go Test It was going to be a small, simple product which would take a few months to build and then mostly look after itself. (In retrospect: Hahaha!) I wasn&#8217;t sure where it was going to go, but I wanted to keep my options open, so I also <a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2009/03/31/doing-a-phd.html'>applied to do a PhD</a> in Cambridge.</p>

<p>I had to propose a PhD topic, and I made up something ad-hoc. I realised that most interesting things are created by individuals, not organisations, and that the reputation and personal network of those individual people is key. And I saw a problem: most things happen online, but fragmented across lots of different websites (including private databases such as CRM systems), so the information is barely useful. I wanted to pull this together and analyse it; I saw this as a route to learning more effectively, by using my network of professional contacts.</p>

<p>To make it sound more academic and less startuppy, I padded the PhD proposal with a bit of blah-blah about machine learning, natural language processing, citation analysis and social graph analysis. But of course my plan was to turn it into a startup eventually. I got my place in Cambridge, got the research funding, moved back into college &#8211; then realised that doing Go Test It and a PhD at the same time was madness, changed my mind, and withdrew from the PhD just a week after I had started. Oh well, interesting experience. I hope I didn&#8217;t waste too many people&#8217;s time.</p>

<p>Around that time I was talking to <a href='http://www.red-gate.com/'>Red Gate</a>, who were interested in acquiring Go Test It, and we closed that deal in November 2009. The plan was that I would stay there for 10 months to hand it over and get it standing on its own feet. We embarked on a big customer development push to figure out who our customers really were and what they really wanted, and we learnt a lot. It was good.</p>

<p><strong>Rapportive comes into being</strong></p>

<p>Other things were happening around that time. My friends <a href='http://twitter.com/rahulvohra'>Rahul</a> and <a href='http://www.samstokes.co.uk/'>Sam</a> were interested in doing a new startup, having worked together at <a href='http://mo.jo'>mo.jo</a> before. I had talked to them about my ideas, originally intended for the PhD, of &#8220;fixing CRM&#8221; by integrating it with social data, and we started thinking about turning it into a startup sooner rather than later.</p>

<p>Rahul came up with some user interface ideas and started coding them up in January; Sam joined in and engineered the backend. Our plan was that I would stay full-time on Go Test It, and fund the other two from my earn-out until October 2010, which is when Go Test It was to be fully handed over to Red Gate. Then I would join them full-time on the new startup. It sounded like a good plan.</p>

<p>Rahul and Sam put together a prototype of Rapportive in a few weeks; we showed it to a few people and they seemed to like it. We put up a simple one-page website, with a few pictures and an install button, so that we had something we could show to potential investors. It wasn&#8217;t much. We hadn&#8217;t even written a privacy policy because we were expecting it to only go out to a small number of people.</p>

<p><strong>And then&#8230; OMGWTFBBQ</strong></p>

<p>What happened then was <a href='http://twitter.com/plc/status/9968421868'>a tweet</a> by our friend <a href='http://twitter.com/plc'>Pete</a> to <a href='http://twitter.com/zee'>Zee</a> of <a href='http://thenextweb.com/'>The Next Web</a>. I had never imagined that a single tweet could be so powerful. Zee loved what he saw and <a href='http://thenextweb.com/apps/2010/03/04/gmail-slick-social-crm-tool/'>wrote it up immediately</a>. Within a day we also had rave write-ups on <a href='http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/gmail_social_crm_plugin_rapportive.php'>ReadWriteWeb</a> (&#8220;stop what you are doing and install this plug-in!&#8221;), then <a href='http://lifehacker.com/5486082/rapportive-replaces-gmail-ads-with-contact-info-is-very-cool'>Lifehacker</a> and <a href='http://webworkerdaily.com/2010/03/05/rapportive-gmail-crm/'>WebWorkerDaily</a> and dozens of smaller blogs and news sites&#8230; thousands of people raving about us on Twitter&#8230; and within that day, over 10,000 users signed up.</p>

<p>10,000 users in one day. That&#8217;s like a fairly large stadium full of people using our software. I had never worked on anything with more than a couple of hundred users before. It&#8217;s hard to describe how that felt.</p>

<p>We were doing nothing but frantically commenting on blog posts, replying to tweets, emails and Skype contacts, and scaling up our servers. Thank goodness for <a href='http://heroku.com/'>Heroku</a>, which made the scaling incredibly easy. We had a few periods of slowness and had to temporarily disable some features, but we never went down. Our servers were continuously handling over 20 requests per second, but we were taking care of our users and giving individual responses to everyone who needed one.</p>

<p>We got a tremendous amount of love from our users, both for the product and for responding swiftly and helpfully to any queries. The vast majority of people who originally signed up are continuing to use it now, and new people are signing up every day.</p>

<p>All of a sudden, our time is incredibly precious. We want to continue to develop Rapportive quickly and continue making something which people really want. We are moving at a very rapid pace, because every day, we have the opportunity to make tens of thousands of people happy.</p>

<p><strong>So&#8230; what about Go Test It?</strong></p>

<p>This success, great as it was, put me in a difficult situation. I was still full-time on Go Test It, and we were just ramping up development to build several big, important features which our customers really wanted. And at the same time, Rapportive needed me more every day.</p>

<p>We had always been very open with the directors of Red Gate as to what was was going on with Rapportive, and so we discussed what we should do. Eventually we decided that Rapportive needed me most, and Go Test It wasn&#8217;t yet ready to stand on its own feet, so we would shut Go Test It down gracefully.</p>

<p>It was a very hard decision, probably one of the hardest I have yet had to make. Red Gate, I and all the others who had worked on it had put a lot of time, effort and money into Go Test It. I was also emotionally invested; after all, this was my first own product. But the opportunity offered by Rapportive was just so disproportionately huge. Killing Go Test It quickly and painlessly was the right decision.</p>

<p>Fortunately the damage was quite limited. Only a small number of customers were using Go Test It regularly, and we found alternative solutions for them. We had a vesting schedule, so the majority of the money from the acquisition went back to Red Gate. There were a few other people working on the project too; they had to find new things to work on, but they are all very talented so it&#8217;s not difficult for them to find work. And most importantly, for me at least: I managed to stay friends with everybody involved. So I think we achieved a good outcome overall.</p>

<p><strong>Onwards and upwards</strong></p>

<p>So here we go: I&#8217;m now a full-time co-founder at Rapportive, and together the three of us are going full steam ahead. We have tens of thousands of people who love what we are doing. We have investors knocking on our door. And we have bucketloads of plans and bright ideas combined with the energy and passion to make them happen.</p>

<p>Life never moves in straight lines; it is full of unexpected surprises. But hey, most surprises turn out to be good ones if you make the most of them. And that&#8217;s what we&#8217;re doing right now.</p>

<p>We&#8217;re in San Francisco and the Bay Area from now until mid-April, so if you&#8217;d like to meet us in person, please <a href='mailto:martin@rapportive.com'>drop me a note</a> &#8211; we&#8217;d love to hear from you!</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Learning about our customers</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/02/23/learning-about-our-customers.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/02/23/learning-about-our-customers.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=368</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ Back in December I wrote about my realisation that we had not been spending enough time learning about our customers at Go Test It. Since then, I have been working hard to catch up in this area, and the last two months have been an incredible experience. Although there&#8217;s still... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>Back in December I <a href='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2009/12/31/how-we-totally-ignored-our-customers.html'>wrote about my realisation</a> that we had not been spending enough time learning about our customers at Go Test It. Since then, I have been working hard to catch up in this area, and the last two months have been an incredible experience.</p>

<p>Although there&#8217;s still a long way to go, we have learnt a lot, and we are getting a much clearer idea of where we need to go in future. And I feel that I am developing another startup skill which will no doubt be valuable in future.</p>

<p>I will be writing about our customer discovery process and things we have learnt in a series of blog posts on the <a href='http://go-test.it/blog'>Go Test It blog</a>. A slightly provocative teaser from my first post of the series:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>A startup&#8217;s purpose is not to make money (at least not initially). Nor is its purpose to build a product (although it won&#8217;t go far without a product). No, the real reason why a startup exists is to <strong>learn</strong> about potential customers and to define a market.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href='http://go-test.it/blog/2010/02/22/learning-about-our-customers.html'>Start reading the new series on the Go Test It blog</a>, <a href='http://feeds.feedburner.com/gotestit'>subscribe to the Go Test It RSS feed</a> and <a href='http://twitter.com/martinkl'>follow me on Twitter</a> to keep track of new posts.</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>How to negotiate a price: Return on Indignation</title>
                <link>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/01/30/how-to-negotiate-a-price-return-on-indignation.html</link>
                <comments>http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/01/30/how-to-negotiate-a-price-return-on-indignation.html#disqus_thread</comments>
                <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <dc:creator>Martin Kleppmann</dc:creator>
                
                    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.yes-no-cancel.co.uk/?p=356</guid>
                
                <description><![CDATA[ As an entrepreneur you have to negotiate things: customer contracts, freelance rates, investments, acquisitions and more. These things are really important, but you probably grew up in a western country where you buy the bar of chocolate for the price it says on the shelf, no more and no less.... ]]></description>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                    <p>As an entrepreneur you have to negotiate things: customer contracts, freelance rates, investments, acquisitions and more. These things are really important, but you probably grew up in a western country where you buy the bar of chocolate for the price it says on the shelf, no more and no less. We&#8217;re not used to negotiating things. So how do you determine a good price?</p>

<p>I&#8217;m sure much has been written about this already, but I&#8217;ve not really read any of it. Instead I made up some principles based on my own bit of experience and a bit of common sense, and maybe you will find them useful.</p>

<p>So let&#8217;s take a look at a negotiation from the point of view of the seller. When you&#8217;re selling something, you want to charge as much as you can get away with. The higher the price, the better for you, i.e. the higher the monetary benefit of the sale to you.</p>
<img class='aligncenter size-full' src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/01/graph1.jpg' height='299' alt='Graph: Value over price (1)' width='500' />
<p>The first bit of money makes a big difference &#8211; maybe you really need it so that you can pay the rent, otherwise you&#8217;ll get kicked out of your house. Within this range, having more money is clearly a lot more valuable for you. However, as the amounts increase and you have secured an acceptable standard of living, I would argue that the <em>benefit</em> of the money <em>to you</em> slows down. Frankly, a top-paid investment banker would barely notice the difference if their salary or bonus was increased or decreased by 50%.</p>

<p>But nevertheless, although it gradually flattens a bit, the line is always increasing. If you can get more out of a deal, it&#8217;s a better deal. At first glance anyway.</p>

<p>However, that&#8217;s not the end of the story. When I am negotiating with someone, this is usually someone I actually <em>want</em> to work with, and I want to stay friends with them. You don&#8217;t want to charge so much that they will simply walk away. And if you&#8217;re in a strong position where the buyer doesn&#8217;t have much choice (eg. because it&#8217;s something urgent and they don&#8217;t have time to find someone else), you don&#8217;t want to abuse your position, as otherwise you will get a bad reputation as someone who takes advantage of others.</p>

<p>Therefore, you should be taking your relationship with the buyer into account. How indignant they will be about your price will depend on a lot of factors (the market value of what you have to offer, how much you charged them previously, how much they can afford, etc). But in general there will be some sort of function describing how happy they are depending on the price (BogoGraph alert!):</p>
<img class='aligncenter size-full' src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/01/graph2.jpg' height='368' alt='Graph: Value over price (2)' width='500' />
<p>Here I plotted in blue the buyer&#8217;s &#8220;goodwill&#8221; (not in any financial sense, just in the sense of &#8220;how much they like you&#8221;). If you charge too much, they will obviously hate you, so the graph goes downhill very rapidly beyond a certain point. You probably don&#8217;t want to go there. I think it is also possible to charge too little, which conveys the message that what you have is not particularly good and not worth very much; but that won&#8217;t offend your buyer nearly as much as overcharging them. So I&#8217;d say that the graph first goes up a little bit, and then goes down a lot.</p>

<p>How do you figure out the shape of that curve for your buyer? That&#8217;s hard. You need to get a few data points, for example you might try asking them for a pretty high price and observing how upset they get. But you&#8217;ve got to be very careful &#8211; don&#8217;t abuse their trust and don&#8217;t waste their time. The longer you spend trying to measure the blue curve, the lower it gets overall (i.e. the more irritated they get with you). It&#8217;s better if you can use external things as reference points &#8211; how much an alternative solution would cost them, how much they have paid for comparable things in the past, the size of their budget (which they probably won&#8217;t tell you but you might be able to guess indirectly).</p>

<p>The value you get out of making the sale is twofold: on the one side the money you get out of it, and on the other side the buyer&#8217;s goodwill (with all of its intangible benefits, such as keeping open potential future deals, recommendations, referrals, general happiness and warm fuzzy feelings). You want both, so let&#8217;s just add the two curves together:</p>
<img class='aligncenter size-full' src='http://martin.kleppmann.com/2010/01/graph3.jpg' height='364' alt='Graph: Value over price (3)' width='500' />
<p>The red line is simply the sum of the blue and the black, and represents the total value you&#8217;re getting out of the sale. Some things to observe:</p>

<ol>
<li>There is a very clear maximum for the total value. This is what you should be aiming at.</li>

<li>The price at which the seller&#8217;s value is maximised is always higher than the ideal price for the buyer (i.e. the red line&#8217;s maximum is further to the right than the blue line&#8217;s maximum). Of course the buyer would prefer to pay less &#8211; if that is not the case, you&#8217;re definitely charging too little.</li>

<li>The blue graph is like quantum mechanics: it changes when you measure it. Keep your negotiations short, simple and clear. Don&#8217;t keep changing your mind, because that just reduces goodwill and thus the total value. Keep in mind that the whole point of this exercise is to stay friends!</li>

<li>The optimal price depends on your weighting of blue curve vs. black curve &#8211; the less you care about the buyer&#8217;s goodwill, the higher the optimal price.</li>

<li>Even if you are playing hard-nosed, it&#8217;s a game of diminishing returns. By pushing harder you will get a bit more money, but the buyer will also get <em>a lot</em> more indignant. The harder you push, the smaller your marginal gains.</li>
</ol>

<p>This brings us to an interesting concept: you can trade in buyer&#8217;s goodwill for more money by adjusting how much you care about how the other party feels. There is a <strong>return on the indignation</strong> of the other party, and it&#8217;s up to you to choose what you want this return to be.</p>

<p>It depends on your character and on the strategic value of the particular deal. I generally work with quite a low return on indignation, i.e. I value goodwill quite highly and won&#8217;t readily trade it for a bit more money. That&#8217;s because:</p>

<ol>
<li>I don&#8217;t find it fun to be hard-nosed, so I&#8217;ll much rather be nice (assuming the other party is also nice), and</li>

<li>I think in terms of long-term value, and I believe that goodwill stays around for a long time, so I&#8217;ll much rather invest in building good long-term relationships than try to extract the maximum monetary value in the short term.</li>
</ol>

<p>That&#8217;s my approach, and I&#8217;m sure others will think differently. But at least, with a framework like this, you can be conscious about your return on indignation.</p>

<p>By the way, if you&#8217;re into pricing products which are not individually negotiated &#8211; quite a different topic &#8211; you should definitely read <a href='http://www.neildavidson.com/dontjustrollthedice.html'>Don&#8217;t just roll the dice</a> by <a href='http://www.neildavidson.com/'>Neil Davidson</a>.</p>
                ]]></content:encoded>
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
